<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The discoverer discovered; or, The lot cast, T.C. taken, and the Babylonish garment found hid under his stuff Being a reply to a late pamphlet, entituled, A discovery of the accursed thing, &amp;c. subscribed T.C. With some remarks upon two papers of John Penny man's. By E.P.</title>
            <author>Penington, Edward, 1667-1701.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 75 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54014</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1143</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R217510</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99829172</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99829172</idno>
            <idno type="VID">33608</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A54014)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 33608)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ;  1975:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The discoverer discovered; or, The lot cast, T.C. taken, and the Babylonish garment found hid under his stuff Being a reply to a late pamphlet, entituled, A discovery of the accursed thing, &amp;c. subscribed T.C. With some remarks upon two papers of John Penny man's. By E.P.</title>
                  <author>Penington, Edward, 1667-1701.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 46 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed and sold by T. Sowle, near the Meeting-house in White-Hart-Count, in Gracious-Street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>E.P. =  Edward Penington.</note>
                  <note>A reply to: Crisp, Thomas. The discovery of the accursed thing in the Foxonian Quakers camp.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Crisp, Thomas, 17th cent. --  Discovery of the accursed thing in the Foxonian Quakers camp --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:33608:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Diſcoverer Diſcovered; OR, The LOT Caſt, <hi>T. C.</hi> Taken, AND THE Babyloniſh GARMENT Found Hid under his STUFF.</p>
            <p>Being a REPLY to a Late Pamphlet, Entituled, <hi>A Diſcovery of the Accurſed Thing,</hi> &amp;c. Subſcribed <hi>T. C.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With ſome Remarks upon Two Papers of <hi>JOHN PENNYMAN</hi>'s.</p>
            <p>By <hi>E. P.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Joſh. 7.18.</hi>
                  </bibl>
And he brought his houſhold, man by man, and <hi>Achan (T. C.)</hi> was taken. <hi>Ver. 25.</hi> And <hi>Joſhua</hi> ſaid, Why haſt thou troubled us? The Lord ſhall trouble thee this day, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Pſal. 109.3.</hi>
                  </bibl>
They compaſſed me about alſo with words of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, and fought against me without a cauſe.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed and Sold by <hi>T. Sowle,</hi> near the <hi>Meeting-houſe</hi> in <hi>White-Hart-Court,</hi> in <hi>Gracious-Street.</hi> 1695.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:33608:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:33608:2"/>
            <head>THE Diſcoverer Diſcovered OR, The LOT Caſt, <hi>T. C.</hi> Taken, AND THE Babyloniſh GARMENT Found Hid under his STUFF.</head>
            <p>WE read, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17. <hi>of a Whore, who made all Nations drunk with the Wine of her Fornications,</hi> and her Name is declared by the Holy Spirit, to be <hi>Myſtery Babylon;</hi> which is not only Literally Fulfilled, in that a Falſe Worſhip hath viſibly overſpread the greateſt part of the World, wherein the true Chriſtian Religion was once planted, and flouriſhed, and viſibly a Falſe Church hath been ſet up and eſtabliſhed, to the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:33608:3"/>
Overthrow of great part of the Doctrine of Chriſt, and the very Form of Godlineſs. But Myſtically alſo, by the prevalency of an Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian Spirit, which by the depth of Deceit and Myſterious working, hath deceived many, ſuffering them ſtill to retain the form, but ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king uſe of them to oppoſe the power of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs: Yea, this Myſtery of Iniquity ſtill works, notwithſtanding the dawning of the Day of God in this laſt Age, hath more mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted her Deeds of Darkneſs, than in many preceding, and that amongſt the moſt refined ſorts of the Profeſſors of Chriſtianity, even amongſt ſome, and now appears through ſome, who once made a great ſhew of being Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of that Church, <hi>which is coming out of the Wilderneſs, leaning upon the Breaſts of her Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved.</hi> And truly both Literally and Myſtical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the Work of this accurſed Harlot hath been to bring People into Confuſion, and to afflict the true Church, and to <hi>make War with the Remnant of her Seed, who hold the Word of their Teſtimony.</hi> Now as certainly as ever that falſe Adulterous Spirit, in any Age ſince the Holy Apoſtle leſt that Prophecy on Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, hath ſought by hidden Practices, as well as open Oppoſition, to undermine the true Church, and the Foundation whereon ſhe is Built, <hi>viz.</hi> Jeſus Chriſt the Rock of Ages, and to introduce a Babyloniſh Confuſion, by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toxicating both the Heads and Hearts of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, in order to betray them from the ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of the Goſpel: So certainly, hath this
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:33608:3"/>
Whoriſh Spirit appeared in theſe our Days, (to the further fulfilling thereof) in many different ſhapes, that (if poſſible) by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivableneſs of unrighteouſneſs, ſhe <hi>might de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the very Elect.</hi> One while acting in Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers from without, not only by outragious Violence, but alſo by wicked Calumnies, like the Dragon, mentioned <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.15. <hi>Caſting out Waters like a Flood.</hi> At other times ſtirring up from within themſelves, ſome <hi>who once received like precious Faith with them,</hi> but being gone from their Firſt Love, and ſo grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing weary of well-doing, have turned their Backs upon the Way of God, and now puſh with the Horn, and kick with the Heel, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe who abide faithful. And though theſe who have broke the Bond of Fellowſhip, wherewith they were once United to the Church, as to the pretended Reaſons of their Diſſatisfaction, as much differ from each other, as Light from Darkneſs, yet like <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pilate,</hi> do readily agree in Perſecuting Chriſt, and <hi>the Members of his Body, which is his Church:</hi> Amongſt whom none have appeared more virulent, both with Tongue and Pen, than <hi>George Keith,</hi> in whoſe Vindication, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo on whoſe Behalf, <hi>Thomas Criſp</hi> hath of late appeared, as a Second to <hi>G. K.</hi> in the Battel he is now Ingaged in: Which ſhews that <hi>T. C.</hi> thinks oppoſing the Quakers a common Cauſe, let it be upon what Terms it will; or elſe, he who formerly clamoured ſo loud againſt Friends, as being degenerated from what they
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:33608:4"/>
were in the beginning, (in that they were (as he alledged) gone too much from the inward to the outward; would not now to ſerve a turn, eat his former words; and that he might curry favour with <hi>G. K.</hi> and avoid the Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency of qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rrelling with him, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by dividing their Intereſts, who in their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to divide the Quakers were perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of one Mind) now recant, and exclaim as much on the other hand, as if they were Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous and Unſound, in not ſufficiently aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the outward; as in his late Paper, Intitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>A Diſcovery of the Accurſed Thing,</hi> &amp;c. now before me ſufficiently appears.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>T. C.</hi> begins with a Slander, not only in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuating, but poſitively accuſing divers, whom he is pleaſed Scornfully to term <q>The Chief Prieſts and Rulers of the Quakers, of deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t Jeſus is the Chriſt, and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Spirit of Antichriſt hath ſhown it ſelf through them, and to prove it, tells us of <hi>VV. Bingley</hi>'s hindring <hi>G. K.</hi> from preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, interrupting him; and when he had done ſpeaking himſelf, bidding the People paſs away, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which he brings as an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>W. B</hi>'s Enmity againſt the preaching the Faith in the Man our Lord Jeſus Chriſt:</q> But what if <hi>W. B.</hi> had another Reaſon for it, where will his Inference be then? I am apt to think it proceeded more from his diſlike to the Preacher, than to the Doctri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e preached: And why (I pray) muſt we be forced to receive a
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:33608:4"/>
Teſtimony, if true, for that reaſon only, from a Perſon we have juſt reaſon to except againſt? Since our Lord, while on Earth, rejected the Teſtimony of the Devil, though true, <hi>and bade him hold his peace, Luke</hi> 4.34, 35. He pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds to tells us, <q>that others have done worſe by him ſince; what worſe then ſay, <hi>He is mad, why hear ye him?</hi>
               </q> I ſuppoſe they did not <hi>take up ſtones to caſt at him,</hi> as the <hi>Jews</hi> ſerved Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 10.31. <q>But they have thereby (ſays he) proved their Spirit, not to be the ſame as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi>'s was; for although ſome preached Chriſt out of Envy to him, yet becauſe Chriſt was preached, he rejoiced:</q> Well, what though the Apoſtle did ſo rejoice, that Chriſt was preached, though in ſome, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy was the Motive thereto, that thereby the Knowledge of the Goſpel might be more Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally ſpread, while the greateſt part of the World was ignorant of the very Hiſtory of Chriſt, as in relation to his Death, Sufferings, Reſurrection and Aſcenſion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yet the ſame Apoſtle ſpeaking of what ſort of Men ſhould riſe up in the laſt Days, leaveth us a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection how to behave our ſelves towards them, he tells us, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. <hi>That in the laſt days pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilous times ſhould come, for men ſhould be</hi> (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other things which he there enume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates) <hi>Lovers of their own ſelves, Boaſters, falſe Accuſers, Fierce, Deſpiſers of thoſe that are good, Heady, High-minded, having the Form of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, but denying the Power thereof. From ſuch</hi> (ſays he) <hi>turn away.</hi> Now I hope <hi>T. C.</hi> will
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:33608:5"/>
readily grant, that the Age wherein we live, ought to be reckoned amongſt the laſt Days, therefore if <hi>VV. B.</hi> by frequent Experience, as well as credible Information, had ground to believe <hi>G. K.</hi> one of thoſe ſort of Men, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in did he amiſs? And if the Meeting were of the ſame Opinion, (which had they not been, I ſuppoſe they would hardly have broke up for his ſaying, <hi>Paſs away Friends</hi>) wherein could they have better demonſtrated their Obedience to the Apoſtles Exhortation? Or wherein have they deviated from the Rule the Apoſtle gave them to walk by in ſuch a Caſe? Though truly it is a queſtion to me (I muſt confeſs) whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>G. K.</hi> deſerve the Character, of having the Form of Godlineſs: I know many are ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied he hath not the Power of Godlineſs, perhaps ſome of his Hearers at <hi>Harp-lane.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He tells his Reader, <q>They Preach this, and they Print the other,</q>but doth not Name who Preached, nor who Printed; a Man may ſuppoſe by his Method of Writing, that every Individual Perſon of his ſo called <hi>Chief Prieſts and Rulers</hi> before-named, have both <hi>Preached and Printed</hi> what he there offers; for he is not ſo kind as to Name either Perſons or Books, which ſhews him an apt Scholar under his new Maſter, <hi>viz.</hi> his highly applauded Reſtorer of ſound Doctrine <hi>G. K.</hi> for he has exactly learnt his Method, of impoſing his ſay ſo upon his Reader, without affording him Opportunities of examining the Quotations, by telling him
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:33608:5"/>
where he may find them, which fault I have to object againſt him, not only in this place, but alſo in other parts of his Paper, as I ſhall have occaſion to remark by and by. But pray where is the Hereſie in aſſerting, <hi>'That the Jews never ſaw the World's Saviour?</hi> Was he not God as well as Man? Had the Godhead no ſhare in mans Salvation, but the Manhood only? Or was the Name Saviour more eminently appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priated to the Manhood? If the Jews had ſeen him to be what he was (<hi>viz.</hi> the Saviour of the World) had they <hi>Crucified the Lord of Life and Glory,</hi> 1 Cor. 7, 8? No ſurely; for though they with their outward Eyes ſaw the Man Jeſus and his Miracles too, yet the Eyes of their minds were blinded, ſo as they could not ſee <hi>the life that dwelt in him</hi> (but denied it, which was revealed to the true believers, and which <hi>John</hi> teſtified <hi>they ſaw,</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.2. and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently did not ſee him to be the world's Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour. And as to his affirming, <q>That the Quakers diſtinguiſh the Lord Jeſus from Chriſt; and mean ſomething in him, and the Light in every Man,</q> 'tis his own falſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, for they do aſſert, That Jeſus of <hi>Nazareth,</hi> who was both God and Man, was and is the Light of the World, and that the rays or beams of Light, which proceed from him the Sun of Righteouſneſs, ſhine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Hearts of all Mankind, and that Chriſt and his Light are not divided, but what he did outwardly in the Fleſh, and what he doth inwardly in Spirit in the inward parts of the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:33608:6"/>
rue believers, is the efficient cauſe of their Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and he, whole Chriſt undivided, is the hope of their Glory.</p>
            <p>But to make the Quakers amends for the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther injuries he hath done them, he will now bring them into good Company, for no leſs then the Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> muſt be erroneous to prove them ſo too, and for my part, I had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be a Heretick in Company with the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle <hi>John,</hi> then Orthodox with <hi>T. C.</hi> But a Man might think how angry ſo ever he might be with the Apoſtle <hi>John,</hi> for ſiding with the Quakers, and affording them ſuch erroneous ſtuff as that of <hi>hearing, ſeeing and handling</hi> the <hi>word of God,</hi> he needed not have ſet old friends variance, and make as if the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> preach't another Goſpel then the Apoſtle <hi>John,</hi> they agreed very well while living, and why ſhould their Epiſtles differ now they are dead? Oh! <hi>T. C.</hi> wants a flyng at <hi>The Saints,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Communion,</hi> &amp;c. and rather then he'l want it long, he'l e'ne quote 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.8. in oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to what the Author of the ſaid Book aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts from 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.1. But for all <hi>T. C.</hi> and whatever he can do or ſay, they are ſtill at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement with each other, and the Quakers with them both, and ſo are like to continue, when <hi>T. C.</hi> and his abettors; <hi>viz.</hi> the whole Gang of Apoſtatized Oppoſers may be gone to their place. And the Foundation whereon they build, and they fix't and eſtabliſhed thereon, will ſtand all the Storms, which ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Battering Rams</hi> by lies and ſlanders,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:33608:6"/>
or <hi>The Painted Harlot</hi> (either maskt or <hi>Vnmaskt</hi>) by her bewitching Sorceries may be permitted to raiſe. Yea, though the <hi>Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> (of the Night) whom he would awake out of their <hi>ſlumber</hi> to his aſſiſtance, may ſtumble in the dark, yet the Light he ſo much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temns, will ſhine more and more, to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering of his confuſed works, and to the finding out 'in whoſe Camp it is, that <hi>The Accurſed thing has been hid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well, though he affirms the Quakers to be erroneous, it ſeems he was ſo himſelf once, if we may take his own confeſſion for true, and did not ſo fully ſee the danger thereof, till convinced by <hi>G. K</hi>'s (I ſuppoſe) effectual preaching (though perhaps <hi>F. B</hi>'s elaborate writings might have a ſhare in <hi>opening his eyes</hi>) then now it ſeems he is got upon the ſtool of Repentance, but he muſt give me leave to think, that for all what that Paper offers of any convincing Argument to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, it would be well for him to Repent of this his Repentance; for if it produce no better effect than ſuch a malicious bundle of ſtuff, as that one Sheet contains, I cannot (nor I believe many other ſober People, even of thoſe who go not under the profeſſion of a Quaker, who may happen to waſt time in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſing it) look upon it to be <hi>the repentance never to be Repented of.</hi> But whatever he the Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer may formerly have been, that doth not make the accuſed ſo too, without more proof then he hath hitherto produced, in his patched
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:33608:7"/>
and peiced, ſtretched or curtailed Quotations: Neither (I ſuppoſe) do the Chriſtian Quakers look upon him, <hi>F. B.</hi> or G. <hi>K.</hi> either, to be fit Perſons to make their Confeſſors nor ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>D. S.</hi> or his friend <hi>G. W.</hi> proper advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates to plead their cauſe for them: They all and every of them, being no better then Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negadoes, who joyn with our Adverſaries, in that, both by ſly Inſinuations, and openly Printed ſlanders, as much as in them lyes, they give away the cauſe, and grant what the moſt malicious Antagoniſts could never yet prove, which could they have done, they would not have left ſo long undone: But to proceed.</p>
            <p>In page ſecond, amongſt divers groſs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections and vile ſlanders (with which his Pamphlet doth ſo abound, that it would be endleſs to trace him through them all) and as it were interwoven therewith, he gives us a kind of confeſſion of Faith, but ſo worded, as if he thereby meant, to exalt the humanity of Chriſt above the Divinity, and plainly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dervalues the Light in every Man, much like the old Profeſſours, and truly puts ſo mean a price on it, as to its ſufficiency, as leſs could not well be, unleſs he had added their thread-bare Epithets of Natural and Diabolical. He ſays, <q>And whatſoever my lot may be from you, I am ſatisfied, greater is he in whom I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve and truſt, even the ſame Jeſus of <hi>Naza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth,</hi> whom you term <hi>Veſſel, Garment,</hi> &amp;c. then the Light in every Man in the World. And
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:33608:7"/>
a little lower, for my truſt and hope is in the mercy of God, for the ſake of my Lord Jeſus of <hi>Nazareth</hi> (without me) and his Obedience and Sufferings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> Now pray Obſerve, he eſteems <hi>the Body,</hi> which the Father <hi>prepared</hi> for the Son, wherein <hi>to do the Fathers will, Heb.</hi> 10.5.7. greater than <hi>the word, which was in the beginning with God, and was God,</hi> John, 1.1. <hi>In whom was Life, and the Life was the Light of Men.</hi> v. 4. <hi>and who was the true Light which Lighteth every Man that cometh into the world,</hi> v. 9. But to make this the more clear: Pray what was that, (which they term <hi>Veſſel, Garment,</hi> &amp;c. 'On whom only <hi>T. C.</hi> fixes his Faith, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies on for Salvation? My Father <hi>I. P.</hi> at whom <hi>T. C.</hi> deſigns this flurt, ſays Part 2. p. 19. of the Collection of his works. <hi>Now the Scriptures do expreſly diſtinguiſh between Chriſt and the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which he wore; between him that came, and the Body in which he came; between the ſubſtance which was vailed, and the vail which vailed it.</hi> Lo I come! a Body haſt thou prepared me. <hi>There is plainly he, and the Body in which he came. There was the outward Veſſel, and the inward Life. This we certainly know, and can never call the bodily Garment Chriſt, but that which appeared and dwelt in the Body. Now if ye indeed know the Chriſt of God, tell us plainly what that is which appeared in the Body? Whether that was not the Chriſt, before it took up the Body, after it took up the Body, and for ever?</hi> Whereby it appears to me that it is on the outward Man of Chriſt, without reſpect to that which <hi>dwelt therein,</hi> Col.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:33608:8"/>
2.19. which my Father here terms <hi>Veſſel Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, &amp;c.</hi> which <hi>T. C.</hi> relies on for Salvation. If that be not his ſentiments, let him lay his matters more cloſely together another time, and not let his malice carry him ſo far into an extream on that hand, whilſt he is labouring to prove thoſe he quarrels with, guilty of an extream on the other hand. He proceeds, <q>I am not aſhamed of this my belief, and hope in him whom ye contemn.</q> Truly if he were not quite ſhameleſs, he might be aſhamed, that he who hath been a hearer of the Quakers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove Thirty years, ſhould now dare to ſay, that they contemn Jeſus Chriſt, whom he can't but have heard frequently preached amongſt them, not only as he appears in Spirit, but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe as he became Man, was born of the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> Suffered under <hi>Pontius Pilate,</hi> was Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, Dead and Buried, roſe again the third day, and aſcended into Heaven, and Sits on the Right Hand of the Majeſty on High, from whence he ſhall come to Judge both the quick and the dead: Therefore he is the more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exuſable, in that he cannot plead ignorance, ſo I ſhall Charge it upon him as a wilful <hi>Error</hi> and that a very <hi>vile and groſs</hi> one too; I muſt needs ſay, he don't go about to <hi>Cloake</hi> it; ſo &amp; as barefac'd ſlander, I return it back upon him, to ſee whether or no it will yet make him bluſh.</p>
            <p>But now his hand is in, he ſcribbles on, and tumbles them out thick and threefold, as much without fear as wit, ſays he, p. <hi>ibid.</hi> 
               <q>You preach a Chriſt Crucified in him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> But
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:33608:8"/>
the Author of this Doctrine being nameleſs, I ſuppoſe he has forgot who it was, and truly I cannot blame him for forgetting, what (I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve) never had any other Foundation then meer imagination. Next comes ſomething <hi>in Print,</hi> there I'le believe him, for I read it in a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſubſcribed <hi>T. C.</hi> but where elſe to find it, I can't tell for my part, therefore ſince he hath not vouchafed to inſtruct me in that point, I ſhall (for all his Capital letter'd remarks) take no farther notice of it at preſent, only, that there are ſo many Scratches, one at the end of almoſt every ſentence, that I queſtion, not but he has ſeverly mangled that quotation, and that openly appears, without any <hi>Miſtery,</hi> to be no part of <hi>a good Chriſtian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Page 3. He ſmooths over <hi>F. B</hi>'s Mock Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lory, and ſpeaks (I doubt not) more then he is able to prove, as in relation to the proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>F. B.</hi> if by they he means the Quakers: But as to <hi>G. K</hi>'s and his adherents ſufferings, he has got a pretty faculty of magnifying them, which if he be not able to make good as there expreſt, by my conſent, he ſhall ſtand on <hi>F. B</hi>'s Pillory next time, as a falſe accuſer, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of thoſe Twelve. In ſhort, that whole Paragraph ſavours of <hi>Tertullus</hi>'s Spirit, though not of his Eloquence, in endeavouring to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the <hi>Overſeers</hi> (as he calls them) that the Quakers aim at the ſubverſion of the Faith, the contrary whereof is moſt true.</p>
            <p>As to his many Quotations out of <hi>G. F</hi>'s Great Myſtery, I have ſpent ſome time in exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:33608:9"/>
them, and find ſome of them ſo ſound, that he hath not been able to corrupt them; and truly I admire to what end he Tranſcribed thoſe, unleſs it were to ſhew us that he cannot bear ſound Doctrine, when <hi>G. F.</hi> is the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſher of it. But for the moſt part, he hath groſly miſrepreſented, abuſed, miſquoted, curtailed and miſapplied paſſages, which in themſelves, taking them as they ſtand in the Book, would not admit of ſuch Conſtructions as he puts upon them, too large to be here re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited; but for a taſte, I here preſent the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der with the following Obſervations, wherein I have endeavoured to reſcue them from the falſe Gloſſes he puts upon them.</p>
            <p>In his third page, that he may not come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind the very worſt of the Oppoſers and Slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers, of that Eminent Servant of Chriſt now at reſt, he ſaith, <q>
                  <hi>G. Fox</hi> being charged to have ſaid, He was Chriſt, he anſwers, It was a Lie; but ſaith, Chriſt in the Male or Female, if he ſpeak, he was Chriſt the Seed, and the Seed was Chriſt. But he ſaid, he did not ſpeak it as a Creature, p. 299.</q> Whereupon <hi>T. C.</hi> makes this Remark, <q>I take him to mean, It was not the Creature <hi>G. F.</hi> but Chriſt in him, that ſaid, He was Chriſt.</q> But if I ſhould tell him, That 'tis either his ſhortneſs of Underſtanding, or aboundings of Malice againſt <hi>G. F.</hi> that makes him run into this miſtake, I know not how he would take it, but however that is the true ſtate of the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:33608:9"/>
Caſe. For the Sentence explains it ſelf, and take him to mean thus, <hi>viz.</hi> He <hi>G. F.</hi> tho' he give the Name Chriſt to ſomething that is in him, and ſpake through him, yet it was no Creature, nor of him <hi>G. F.</hi> but was the Seed which is Chriſt, the ſame in both Male and Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.15. compared with <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.16, and 28. He quotes p. 67. his Words are theſe, <q>Alſo by oppoſing another, they do imply, they are equal with God; for they ſay to an Opponent, <hi>Thou makeſt a great pud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that any ſhould witneſs he is equal with God.</hi>
               </q> 
               <hi>T. C.</hi> ſhould have been ſo fair, as to have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joined to this Quotation, the latter part of <hi>G. F</hi>'s Anſwer, but ſince he hath not I ſhall do it for him. After <hi>G. F.</hi> hath recited a paſſage out of The Catechiſm of the Aſſembly of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, (ſo called) <hi>viz. That the Holy Ghoſt and the Son is equal in Power and Glory with the Father,</hi> he adds, <hi>Yet if any one come to witneſs the Son revealed in him, or come to witneſs the Holy Ghoſt in them, as they that gave out the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; or witneſs the Mind of Chriſt, and witneſs that equal which the Father, that equality which you ſpeak of: You Prieſts deſtroy that which you have put forth in the Nation, and cry out Horrid Blaſphemy.</hi> Thus far G. <hi>F.</hi> and now much good may this Citation do <hi>T. C.</hi> and the <hi>pud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> he has made about it too. But he hath not done with this Point yet, he ſays, <q>G. F. being charged to profeſs Equality with God, he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers, G. Fox<hi>'s words were ſpoken beyond and out of all Creatures,</hi> p. 127.</q> Here is mang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:33608:10"/>
work with a witneſs, he has cut off the Head and Tail of this Sentence, and only left us the middle, which as it lyes together is ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid Sence; for after G. F. had repeated the foregoing paſſage of the Aſſembly of Divines, he in farther Vindication of himſelf, from that foul Aſperſion they had caſt upon him, adds, <hi>Yet nevertheleſs</hi> George<hi>'s words was not ſpoken as ye preach them; for his words were ſpoken beyond all Creatures, and out of all Creatures, and he did not ſay</hi> George Fox. But of this enough, and full enough to ſhew his corrupt Dealings, in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſing a Man who is dead, and ſo not able to anſwer for himſelf; but Malice unbounded, will take into the Graves of the Dead, if poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, to make the Objects of their hatred ſtink in the Noſtrils of the Living; but when all is done, they for the moſt part make themſelves ſtink alive, when the Memory of good Men, though they have been never ſo much ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lized, is as the Odour of ſweet Ointment, and the good ſavour, which the remembrance of their Virtues, hath left upon the Spirits of thoſe who ſurvive, Embalms their Names to Poſterity.</p>
            <p>So having, (I hope) cleared this Point to the Impartial Rea er, I ſhall next take a view of a Scoff he puts upon the Quakers, for <q>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing a being guided by an Infallible Spirit, for which he quotes p. 105.</q> which whole Paragraph hath relation to the Infallibility of the Spirit of God, which ſaith <hi>G. F. is now poſſeſſed and witneſſed amongſt thoſe called Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers.</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:33608:10"/>
Now, either the Spirit of God is a fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible Spirit, which let him aſſert if he dare, or 'tis not communicated to Mankind, contrary to 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.7. and <hi>Joel</hi> 2.28, 29. or 'tis not neceſſary towards making a Man a Chriſtian, contrary to <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.9. or elſe <hi>T. C</hi>'s Cavil is groundleſs. And as to what he mentions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> I wont under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take to reſolve his Doubt, but I queſtion not at all <hi>Peter</hi>'s knowing by the Revelation of the Infallible Spirit of God, and by no outward Means, that <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Sapphira</hi> had <hi>Lied a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Holy Ghoſt</hi> in that Caſe, <hi>Acts</hi> 5. and that was 1636. Years ago, inſtead of his 36, and for all that it is not <hi>loſt</hi> yet. For I will undertake to prove (if <hi>T. C.</hi> be ſo far dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated from the very form of ſound words, as to deny it) that the Infallible Spirit of Chriſt, is now poſſeſſed and witneſſed amongſt all true Chriſtians whatſoever: For if they have it not, the Apoſtle tells us, <hi>they are none of Chriſt's,</hi> and if not Chriſt's, then no true Chriſtians. Moreover I Challenge <hi>T. C.</hi> to prove if he can, that ever any real Quaker, owned as ſuch among the Quakers, aſcribed Infallibility to any Man, or number of Men, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe than as immediately influenced by the guidance of the Infallible Spirit of God; for his Inferences without Proof will but ſhew his Envy; and conſidering how much he hath ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted himſelf not only an Adverſary, but alſo an unfair Adverſary, will not ſatisfie rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Men. Now to prove him guilty of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairneſs
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:33608:11"/>
in this very particular, I ſhall Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe his Quotation, and then that Paragraph in the Book it ſelf, which compared together, will ſufficiently clear up the Matter. <hi>T. C.</hi> p. 3, and 4. <q>Alſo they ſay, <hi>How can you but delude the People who are not Infallible?</hi> p. 82. Hereby oppoſing others, they imply (not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Spirit, but) themſelves to be Infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</q> Now <hi>G. F</hi>'s own words run thus. <hi>And how can they but delude People, that are not Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible, and are none of Chriſt's, which have not the Spirit which is Infallible, and are not Miniſters of the Goſpel, which is the Power of God, which is Infallible?</hi> Pray what Credit is there to be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to this Man's Quotations or Aſſertions ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Well I would adviſe him, the next time he writes, either to be Honeſter in his Quotations, or elſe take that Courſe altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which he hath in part already, <hi>viz.</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Name, Book, nor Author.</p>
            <p>In his fourth Page he quarrels with <hi>G. F.</hi> for calling Chriſt, <hi>The Root of God;</hi> and nothing will ſerve him, but he muſt put it in Capital Letters, with a <q>This I think is Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous, at the end of it;</q> nay it ſticks ſo in his Stomach, that p. 5. he muſt have t'other fling at it; and there he comes in with a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentheſis, and ſays, <q>But I think this their Doctrine is the Root of Blaſphemous Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm: But why ſo angry I pray, Is not Chriſt mentioned as a <hi>Root?</hi>
               </q> 
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.18. And is not Chriſt <hi>God</hi>'s? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.23. Therefore
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:33608:11"/>
where is the Blaſphemy, in ſaying, Chriſt is <hi>the Root of God;</hi> I think he may as well be called <hi>the Root, as the Foundation of God,</hi> ſee 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.11. compared with 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.19. ſince it refers to Men, and not to God.</p>
            <p>About the beginning of p. 5. he is guilty of a groſs Perverſion, and it looks like a wilful one too, for he hath omitted not only one whole Sentence; but the word <hi>and</hi> at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the next, which greatly alters the Sence, beſides his omitting what followed, which is Explanatory of <hi>G. F</hi>'s meaning, the paſſage is ſo clear in it ſelf, and <hi>T. C</hi>'s abuſe ſo viſible, that I ſhall only rehearſe it, firſt as quoted by him; and ſecondly, as it ſtands in the Book it ſelf, and then leave it to the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial to judge. <hi>T. C</hi>'s Citation runs thus; <q>One ſays ſuch be in Error, that knows no Chriſt but a Chriſt within. <hi>G. F.</hi> anſwers, <hi>They that profeſs a Chriſt without them, have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Chriſt</hi> (mark that) <hi>within them, here is two,</hi> ſays G. F. <hi>p.</hi> 254.</q> Now the Book it ſelf ſays, <hi>And they that profeſs a Chriſt without them, have a Chriſt without them, <hi>and</hi> another Chriſt within them, here is two; for if it be not the ſame Chriſt that ended all Types, and Figures, and Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows. If it be not him that is within them, they have not the Poſſeſſion of the Subſtance, nor the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of the true Chriſt; but who have not Chriſt, the end of Types, Shadows and Figures in them, they are among Antichriſts, and falſe Chriſts, and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:33608:12"/>
they that have a form of Godlineſs, can confeſs a Chriſt without them, and not within them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A little lower in the ſame p. 5. he has quite maimed another Quotation, by cutting it in two in the middle; but as much as he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joints it, it is not paſt ſetting together again, and that ſhall be my work at this time. <hi>T. C.</hi> brings in G. F. ſaying, <q>
                  <hi>The Devil was in thee, thou ſaiſt thou art ſaved by a Chriſt without thee, and ſo haſt recorded thy ſelf a Reprobate,</hi> p. 250.</q> This is all he can afford; but G. F. proceeds, <hi>And ignorant of the Myſtery of Chriſt within thee; for without that thou doſt not know Salvation.</hi> I would ask T. C. wherein doth G. F. contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict the Apoſtle <hi>Paul?</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5. <hi>Examine your ſelves whether you be in the faith: prove your own ſelves. Know you not your own ſelves, how that Jeſus Chriſt is in you, except ye be Reprobates?</hi> For my part I cannot perceive how G. F. can be Erroneous, and the Apoſtle Orthodox, for whatever T. C. may think, they ſeem to me no ways contradictory to each other.</p>
            <p>The next Quotation I take notice of in the ſame Page, is very unfair, if deſigned; but however I will be ſo fair to him, as to take his Excuſe, if he will plead Ignorance and want of Underſtanding; what difference there is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween words incloſed in a Parentheſis, and where there is no Parentheſis: But if he doth underſtand it, then it is no longer weakneſs, but wickedneſs; the words are theſe, <q>
                  <hi>All be in the fancy that be out of the witneſſing Chriſt that ſuffered within them,</hi> p. 131.</q> Now who would
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:33608:12"/>
have concluded any other, but that G. F. un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dervaluing the Sufferings of Chriſt without the Gates of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> had publiſhed, that his Sufferings were within Man only. But now take it with the Parentheſis as the Book hath it, <hi>viz. And ſo all be in the fancy, that be out of the ſtate of witneſſing Chriſt <hi>(that Suffered)</hi> within them.</hi> This alters the Caſe, for 'tis all one as if he ſhould have ſaid, And ſo all be in the fancy, that be out of the ſtate of witneſſing Chriſt that ſuffered without, to be revealed within them; and this is according to Chriſt's own words, <hi>John</hi> 14.17. <hi>He dwelleth with you, and ſhall be in you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, p. 6. <q>One ſays, The Seed to whom the Promiſe of Salvation is made, is, or hath been Sinners. G. F. anſwers, <hi>The Promiſe is to the Seed—which Seed is the Hope Chriſt that purifies—and this Seed never ſinned,</hi> p. 324. Says T. C. Hereby G. F. does imply, That the Promiſe of Salvation was to Chriſt, as if he had need of Salvation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> Whatever <hi>Jugling</hi> T. C. may pretend to find in G. F. I cannot acquit T. C. of <hi>Jugling,</hi> for he hath left out one Sentence, which manifeſts that G. F. was far from meaning, that Chriſt ſtood in need of Salvation; for between the word purifies, and this Seed, inſtead of T. C's ſcratch, G. F. hath this Expreſſion, <hi>And hereby is the Creature come to know its liberty among the Sons of God;</hi> which plainly cuts off T. C's Cavil, if he had but had the Honeſty to have inſerted it: And in Vindication of G. F's aſſerting, That the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:33608:13"/>
Seed to whom the promiſes were made was Chriſt, read <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.16. and that the Creature comes no other way to be partaker of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, than as found in Chriſt, read <hi>v.</hi> 28, 29.</p>
            <p>But now as if he thought the errors he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends the Quakers are guilty of in point of Doctrine, not ſufficient to do his work, as perhaps being conſcious of the weakneſs as well as groundleſneſs, of all his loud clamours a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them on that Score, he will e'ne take up his old predeceſſor's Argument, <hi>John</hi> 19.12. <hi>If thou let this Man go, thou art not</hi> Caeſar<hi>'s friend.</hi> And rather then fail of his ſpight, he would if he could render them obnoxious to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and for that end quotes a paſſage concerning <hi>Monarchy,</hi> which he Fathers upon G. F. but whether ever wrote, or at leaſt ſo wrote by G. F. I know not, for the Book is nameleſs, and ſo his clamour not worth the minding. No more is that concerning the <hi>Houſe of Lords;</hi> for he quotes no Quakers Book, but one of <hi>John Pennyman</hi>'s, which manifeſts that he is willing to take any thing upon truſt, (eſpecially what was written by ſo dearly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved a Brother in the common cauſe, as the ſaid J. P.) that will but ſerve for an objection againſt G. F. in particular, or the Quakers in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral. And as for <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> he hath taken a large ſtep ſince he left the Quakers, if he be got to them again; however they will have but little honour by ſuch a Member, nor are we in danger of following ſuch an example. Now upon the whole of theſe three Paragraphs, I
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:33608:13"/>
have this to remark, that the method of his expoſing them to the world, ſhews his great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that the Chief Men in the Nation may be ſet againſt us; for leaſt they ſhould not be ſo far taken notice of, as he would have them, they muſt be all in Capital Letters, that ſo making a great Figure in that page, the Reader might be taken with more than ordinary cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity to ſee what that was, and then perhaps it might light into the hands of ſome, that owed the Quakers as little good-will as <hi>T. C.</hi> doth, and ſo from one to another, it might at laſt come to the ears of the King, Peers and Biſhops: And what then? They are Men of more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, than to take one Deſerters mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Libel, againſt a Body of People, of whoſe peaceable behaviour, this Nation hath had ſo long experience, even under all the Altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and various Changes which have hap'ned, in relation to Government, ever ſince they were a People.</p>
            <p>His applauding <hi>D. S.</hi> as a <q>
                  <hi>Chriſtian Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker,</hi> and running againſt the Twenty Four who diſowned him,</q> ſhews that he, <hi>D. S. F. B. G. K.</hi> &amp;c. mentioned in that paragraph, are all Birds of a feather, and no wonder then if they flock together. And as for <q>
                  <hi>G. W</hi>'s <hi>er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors and evil deeds</hi> he hints at, let him make the beſt of them, I queſtion not but <hi>G. W.</hi> is able to anſwer him, if he thinks it worth his while, which truly I think hardly is.</q> And as to his complaint in behalf of <hi>G. K.</hi> in relation to the proceedings in <hi>Penſylvania,</hi> againſt him
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:33608:14"/>
and his adherents; <hi>S.</hi> J. hath already given an account how they were managed, in his <hi>State of the Caſe,</hi> &amp;c. and therein vindicated himſelf, and thoſe concerned with him, from the aſperſion caſt upon them. Perhaps he may alledge, that <hi>G. K.</hi> hath anſwered that Book, and ſtated things otherways: Yet how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, he ought in juſtice to ſuſpend his verdict, till he hears what proof <hi>S.</hi> J. will bring in defence of what he hath written, which (God ſparing him Life) I queſtion not but he may be able to produce.</p>
            <p>He ſays p. 7. <q>It is not my intent to make void or undervalue the Light of Chriſt, or Spirit of God within, and obedience thereto; for its our duty to walk in the Light, but not to build thereon.</q> If he had ſaid ſo as to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the benefit which accrued to Mankind, by the death of Chriſt, I would ſaid ſo too; but I cannot like him divide Chriſt, by aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing the whole work to Chriſt without, and making that the ſole Foundation of the true Faith: For unleſs Chriſt work inwardly in Mens Hearts by his Spirit, <hi>not only the will but the deed alſo</hi> Phil. 2.13. And unleſs the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Sanctify them through his word, whoſe word is truth</hi> John 17.17. To them the Blood of Chriſt ſhed without the Gates of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> will be of no effect. Now <hi>The word which took Fleſh</hi> is Chriſt and <hi>His Life is the Light of Men,</hi> John 1.4. therefore to ſay it is not our duty to build thereon is erroneous, and tends to the undervaluing of Chriſt, who ought not to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:33608:14"/>
be divided. This is other Doctrine then Chriſt preached, John 12.36. <hi>While ye have the Light, believe in the Light, that ye may be the Children of the Light.</hi> And how can I believe in the Light, if I have no dependance thereon? How can I obey the Light or Spirit, or walk therein (which he grants is our duty) if I muſt not build upon it? The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi>'s preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was attended <hi>with the demonſtration of the Spirit, and of Power:</hi> And the reaſon he gives is, <hi>That your Faith ſhould not ſtand in the wiſdom of men, but in the Power of God,</hi> 1 Cor. 2.4, 5. which Power of God is Chriſt, not only as he was manifeſted outwardly, but alſo as he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears inwardly, and is certainly what is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently demonſtrated in that Chapter. And further he tells the <hi>Coloſſians,</hi> Chap. 1.27. <hi>That Chriſt in them was the hope of their Glory.</hi> And <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.24. <hi>We are ſaved by hope.</hi> Muſt not we build then upon the ſaying hope of Glory, Chriſt in us? Strange Doctrine ſurely! How elſe can we <hi>Fly for refuge, to lay hold upon the hope ſet before us?</hi> Or how elſe ſhall we experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence <hi>Hope to be as an Anchor of our Souls, both ſure and Stedfaſt?</hi> Heb. 6.18, 19. Or did the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle preach falſe Doctrine, and deny the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of Chriſt in the Fleſh? No ſurely; no more do the Quakers now. How muſt <hi>the whole lump be Leavened,</hi> if we have not our Faith fixed on him, <hi>who is the Leaven of the Kingdom, and is hid in the three meaſure of Meal, viz.</hi> the Soul, Body and Spirit? <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.33. But no wonder that Men err when they walk
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:33608:15"/>
in Darkneſs, and deſpiſe that Light by which they ſhould be preſerved from it.</p>
            <p>Having ſhewed his contradiction to Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, I ſhall now proceed, and take notice that he brings in divers paſſages, in p. 7. and the beginning of p. 8. with a <hi>Say they:</hi> But he neither informs us out of what Book he took them, nor for the moſt part, who was the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor: Probably becauſe he would take the more Latitude to abuſe them undiſcovered; for he makes no conſcience of quoting falſly, and perverting <hi>G. F</hi>'s writings, as I have ſhewed above, though he has in quoting that Book often referred to the pages: Therefore I cannot think I do him any wrong in ſuſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe Quotations not to be genuine; and ſince he hath not given me the opportunity of examining whether they be ſo or no, as ſuch I ſhall paſs them over.</p>
            <p>But now comes a ſhrewd caſe of Conſcience, the very Maſter-peice of this <hi>Babel-Builders</hi> Structure, which demonſtrates that he is in confuſion, or elſe certainly would never have let ſuch a blunder be expoſed to the World.</p>
            <p>He ſays p. 8. <q>Now I appeal to their Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, whether or no if our Lord Jeſus, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is believed on and obeyed, ſo as to have his perfect work in the Heart to Regenerate, and make all things a-new, whether this can be, and the work of Regeneration not known?</q> Truly a very notable queſtion, and very nicely diſtinguiſhed: I dare believe he made no uſe of G. K's either Logick or
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:33608:15"/>
Philoſophy in this appeal. But I admire that G. K. ſhould take no more care of his Pupil in his Divinity, than to ſuffer him to fumble thus, I believe he would not have ſuffered ſuch a thing to eſcape his Cognizance among his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſort of Scholars. However to pleaſe T. C. I will readily grant, that when a Man is become Regenerate, he hath known the work of Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. But if his Queſtion in the ſenſe he means it (which truly ſeems to me, to be what he drives at) hath reſpect only to a Faith on Chriſt as he is without, excluding the operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Light and Spirit within, and Faith therein, then I deny it: For Regeneration is a qualification, rendring a Man capable of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering the Kingdom of Heaven, then conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently he muſt be in a ſtate of Salvation, but <hi>John Rev.</hi> 21.23, 24. After he hath given an account of the Glory of the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> ſays, <hi>The Glory of the Lord did lighten it, and the Lamb is the Light thereof. And the Nations of them which are ſaved ſhall walk in the Light of it.</hi> And the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaking concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>the Elect, whoſe Souls were purified in obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the truth through the Spirit,</hi> ſays, <hi>Being Born again, not of corruptible Seed, but of incorruptible, by the word of God which liveth and abideth for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.22, 23.</p>
            <p>As for what he relates concerning a Preachers <hi>deifying G. F.</hi> it is an old thred-bare ſtory, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten recited by divers oppoſers, and hath been already anſwered, and ſo I need ſay the leſs to it; all that I ſhall obſerve is, that they do
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:33608:16"/>
not all tell one Tale, neither (to my own knowledge, having compared them) is this the ſame with what hath been Printed by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther perſon, referring to this very letter.</p>
            <p>I have one paſſage more to take notice of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I leave him, and truly I cannot tell how to paſs by it, it being indeed his Reflections on that Perſon that firſt occaſioned me to take this work in Hand, who in Truth deſerves to have a better Pen imployed in his Defence than mine; but however ſuch as it is, though it may fall ſhort of the end propoſed, through want of Skill and Experience in me, how to manage an Argument, yet may ſerve to teſtifie the Value I have for, and the Filial Reſpect I bear to the Memory of a worthily Eſteemed, deſervedly Honoured, and truly Honourable Father: Who though by <hi>F. B.</hi> (whom this Man vindicates) in way of Contempt be term<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>a Devout Heathen,</hi> was well known (by thoſe who knew the Truth in which he lived, and in which he died, and had any Acquaintance with him) to be a ſincere Chriſtian, and true Miniſter of the Goſpel of Chriſt, <hi>not of the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> only, <hi>but of the Spirit,</hi> as was the Apoſtle <hi>Paul:</hi> And his endeavour was to fix People on that Rock which would abide the Storm, and preſerve them from falling, <hi>viz. That ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Rock which followed</hi> Iſrael, <hi>which Rock was Chriſt.</hi> But by reaſon of his vindicating the living and lively Faith of Chriſt ſpiritually re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed in the Heart, without which the Lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Faith, would be ſo far from ſaving them,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:33608:16"/>
that it would but add to their Condemnation; I ſay, for this his Zealous Defence of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel of Chriſt, and exalting the Spirit above the Fleſh, (though they could never prove him guilty of denying or ſlighting the outward Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of Chriſt in the Fleſh) he was not without a ſhare of the Slanders and Calumnies of Adverſaries of all ſorts, while living; and though he hath now been dead ſeveral Years, yet T. C. will not let him reſt in his Grave, but muſt rake in his Aſhes, for Dirt to fling at him: And truly he is an Author who hath been much quoted by T. C. in moſt, if not all the Pamphlets he hath publiſhed againſt that Church, whereof my ſaid Father was an Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Member: Formerly his Perverſions of his Writings tended to make him ſpeak contrary, when Dead, to his Brethren, with whom he was in true Unity while Living, and then T. C. could quote him as Authentick, and by him approved for ſound Doctrine: But ſince that would not effect his Deſign, now his Writings muſt be Apocryphal, and he a Publiſher of falſe Doctrine, to prove the Quakers guilty thereof too; but how far he falls ſhort in his Proofs I hope to evince by and by. He hath had ſeveral touches at him in ſome of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going Paragraphs of his Pamphlet, but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out naming either Book or Author, but now in the cloſe to pin the Basket, he gives us three Letters of his Name, <hi>viz. Iſ. P.</hi> yet names no Book neither: But I knowing that The Queſtion to Profeſſors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> hath been a
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:33608:17"/>
Choak-pear to the meer Letter-mongers of our Times; I imagined it might be out of that Book that he took his Quotations, which he quarrels ſo with, and upon peruſing it found them there; and therefore for the Honour I bear to the Memory of ſo near a Relation, and ſo good a Man, I ſhall endeavour to wipe off the Aſperſion which T. C. caſts upon him. He ſays, <q>And it's aſtoniſhing to behold how they contemn our Lord Jeſus, and Deifie him, (<hi>viz.</hi> G. F.) thereby making way for themſelves to be ſo many Chriſt's, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by <hi>Iſ. P</hi>'s ſaying, <hi>Doth not the name be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to every Member as well as to the Head?</hi>
               </q> Now if the whole Query, from whence thoſe words are taken, do not tend to contemn our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, or for making way for themſelves to be ſo many Chriſts, then is T. C. a falſe Accuſer; and to prove him ſuch, I ſhall tranſcribe the Query <hi>Verbatim,</hi> only with the Addition of thoſe Scriptures at length in Parentheſis's, which he quotes in proof of his Aſſertions, and leave it to the unbyaſſed to judge, whether it hath ſuch a tendency or no? Or whether it be not ſound Apoſtolical Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine? Part 2. p. 15. of <hi>Iſ. P</hi>'s Collection, Qu. 24. <hi>Is not the Subſtance, the Life, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointing called Chriſt, where-ever it be found? Doth not the Name belong to the whole Body (and every Member in the Body) as well as to the Head? Are they not all of one, yea, all one in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointing? Was not this the great deſire of his Heart to the Father, that they all might be one,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:33608:17"/>
even as the Father and Chriſt were one,</hi> John 17.21, 23. (That they all may be one, as thou Father art in me, and I in thee, that they alſo may be one in us: I in thee, and thou in me, that they may be made perfect in one.) <hi>And ſo being one in the ſame Spirit, one in the ſame Life, one in the ſame Nature,</hi> 2 Pet. 1.4. (Whereby are given unto us exceeding great and precious Promiſes, that by theſe you might be Partakers of the Divine Nature) <hi>even Partakers of God's Holineſs,</hi> Heb. 12.10. (For they verily cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtened us after their own Pleaſure, but he for our Profit, that we might be partakers of his Holineſs) <hi>Chriſt is not aſhamed to call them Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,</hi> Heb. 2.11. (For both he that ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth, and they who are ſanctified, are all of one; for which cauſe he is not aſhamed to call them Brethren) <hi>nor is the Apoſtle aſhamed to give them the Name Chriſt together with him,</hi> 1 Cor. 12.12. (For as the Body is one, and hath many Members, and all the Members of that one Body, being many, are one Body; ſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo <hi>is</hi> Chriſt) <hi>The Body is the ſame with the Head; one and the ſame in Nature; and doth not the Name belong to the Nature in the whole? So that the Name is not given to the Veſſel, but to the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to the heavenly Treaſure, to that which the Lord from Heaven begets in his own Image and Likeneſs, of his own Subſtance, of his own Seed, of his own Spirit and pure Life.</hi> Thus far my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Now I obſerve upon the whole, That he doth not aſſert, that every Member is a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct Chriſt, (any more than every Member
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:33608:18"/>
is a diſtinct Body) <hi>thereby making way for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be ſo many Chriſt's,</hi> (as <hi>T. C.</hi> falſly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms.) But ſo far as every one is a Member of the Body, whereof Chriſt is Head, and of the Anointing, from whence the Name Chriſt is derived; ſo far have they a Title to the Name Chriſt, or Anointed, as being Chriſted or Anointed, begotten by him the Incorrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Seed, ſanctified through his Blood, and thereby made Partakers of his Righteouſneſs, are become one with him, his Brethren, Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the ſame Father, Hei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s of the ſame Glory, according to their Meaſures. Neither doth this tend to the contemning of Chriſt, for this Union doth not imply an equality, though the Members are all anointed with the ſame Holy Oil as is Chriſt the Head, yet <hi>he is anointed with the Oil of Gladneſs above his Fellows, Heb.</hi> 1.9. The Scripture abounds in ſetting forth the Myſtical Union between Chriſt and his Church, as particularly <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. where the Apoſtle giving Directions, how Husbands and Wives ought to demean themſelves towards each other, ſtirs them up to mutual Love, by the Example of Chriſt's Love to his Church, and comparing their near Alliance to each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, by the Union of Chriſt with his Church, he ſaith, v. 30. <hi>We are Members of his Body, of his Fleſh, and of his Bones:</hi> Then certainly eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Member is partaker of the ſame Life, the ſame Blood, the ſame Strength, the ſame Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and the ſame Subſtance with the Head, though not in the ſame degree; a lively Type
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:33608:18"/>
whereof, was the <hi>Ointment that was upon</hi> Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron<hi>'s head, that went down to the very skirts of his garment,</hi> Pſal. 133.2. So that 'twas the ſame Ointment ſtill, (though not in that quantity) which was upon the Head, that ran down to the very Skirts, but the Head was the place from whence this Ointment flowed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Inferior Parts.</p>
            <p>Now having taken notice of what paſſages in his Paper to me ſeemed moſt worthy of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, as deſerving to have a black Line drawn over them, and a Mark ſet on them, for the Scandals, Abuſes and Unfairneſs contained in them, (though I muſt needs confeſs, his whole Sheet from one end to the other, is little elſe but one continued Slander) I ſhall draw to a Concluſion; ſolemnly declaring, That it is not Malice (I can truly ſay) againſt the Man that drew theſe Lines from me, but Trouble to ſee his groſs Perverſions of good Mens Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings and Meanings, (and that I fear againſt his own Knowledge) after this manner; and the very worſt I wiſh to him, or the reſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned with him in this ill Work, is their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance: That their many hard Words and bitter Speeches againſt the Church of Chriſt in general, or any Member or Members thereof in particular, may not be laid to their Charge, at the great Day of Judgment; when not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly all Actions, but the Secrets of all Hearts ſhall be laid open, and a Juſt Reward rendred by Chriſt to every Man according to his Doings.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>E. P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:33608:19"/>
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>SInce the writing of the above, I obſerved that at the cloſe of his Paper. <hi>T. C.</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers to a former Book of his, Entituled, <hi>Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>madverſions, &amp;c.</hi> whereupon I peruſed that Book, (which I had never done before) and therein found ſufficient cauſe for Animadverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon his Animadverſions: However at preſent I ſhall take notice but of two paſſages of my Fathers which ſo affront him, that the occaſion he takes to quarrel with them, takes up a conſiderable part of that Book; and very angry he is with <hi>G. W.</hi> for writing any thing in Vindication of them; but however though I ſhould incur his Diſpleaſure too, as a Duty I owe to the Dead, I ſhall endeavour it, by taking notice of thoſe Paſſages, and comparing them with ſome other in the ſame Book Expla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natory of them, in the mean time paſſing over the Reflections he caſts upon <hi>G. W.</hi> as know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him able to anſwer for himſelf, (if not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready done) provided he ſee Cauſe.</p>
            <p>The firſt is Part 2. p. 19. of my Father's Works; which I have quoted at large before, but ſhall now take notice of that part which ſo much offends him, and which (if we may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve him) <q>he never ſaw nor heard of before,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:33608:19"/>
                  <hi>Anim.</hi> p. 20.</q> (that he ſhould never find it, till juſt now he has a Mind to Cavil at it; may be ſo, but 'tis ſtrange, probably he means, he never ſaw nor heard it to be falſe Doctrine be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) and is as followeth, <q>
                  <hi>This we certainly know, and can never call the bodily Garment Chriſt, but that which a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>peared and dwelt in the Body.</hi> Now p. 7. He ſays it is evident, it was intended to undervalue our Lord Jeſus his Perſon, as Body and Soul living; neither are ſuch diſtinctions in Scripture, (as <hi>Iſ. P.</hi> makes) ſince Jeſus his Incarnation, but by him made in order to his Contempt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> But for all <hi>T. C</hi>'s haſte, I hope before I leave this Subject, to prove by Scripture, that the Body when mentioned diſtinct from the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity, is not termed Chriſt, but his Body both Dead and Living. When Dead it is in ſo many words called, <hi>The Body of Jeſus,</hi> John 19.38. And he himſelf calls it <hi>a Temple,</hi> John 2.19. which <hi>v.</hi> 21. is explained to be <hi>the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of his Body,</hi> which he, <hi>viz.</hi> Chriſt the Word, (mentioned in the foregoing Chapter) <hi>would raiſe up in three days.</hi> And the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Coloſſians,</hi> diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing between the Divinity and Humanity of Chriſt, ſays, <hi>v.</hi> 16. <hi>For by him were all things created that are in heaven,</hi> &amp;c. But 21, 22, <hi>And you that were ſometimes alienated, and Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies in your mind by wicked works, yet now hath he reconciled in the Body of his fleſh through Death.</hi> Now I would ask <hi>T. C.</hi> Doth my Father deny the Name Chriſt to the Body united to the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:33608:20"/>
Word, or abſtractly, when ſpeaking concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Body only? I affirm, and that I will prove by other Quotations out of the ſame Book, that he owns the Name Chriſt to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to that Body, as it was the Veſſel which contained the Anointing, from whence the Name Chriſt proceeds. Page 6. ſpeaking concerning the Seed of the Woman, he ſaith, <hi>This Seed we know to be the Seed of</hi> Abraham, <hi>the Seed of</hi> David <hi>after the Fleſh, and the Seed of God after the power of an endleſs Life, and we are taught of God to give the due honour to each; to the Seed of God in the firſt place, to the Seed of</hi> David <hi>in the ſecond place:</hi> And that due Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour he farther explains, p. 12. Q. 6. <hi>To whom do the Names and Titles Jeſus and Chriſt, chi fly, and in the firſt place belong? Do they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the Body, which was took by him, or to him who took the Body,</hi> &amp;c? Then it ſeems he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, that in the ſecond place they belong to the Body, in reſpect to him who took the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy: But to clear the Point farther, ſee p. 13. the latter part of Q. 11. <hi>Have we the denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and relation with Chriſt from that which is Spiritual? And hath Chriſt himſelf the Name from, or becauſe of the Body of Fleſh? Nay, nay, the Name Chriſt was from the Anointing, which was in the Body, which run into and filled the Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel. It is true, the <hi>Body</hi> in and by the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion, partakes with him of his <hi>Name;</hi> but the Name belongs chiefly, and moſt properly to the Treaſure in the Veſſel.</hi> Methinks by <hi>T. C</hi>'s leave this may p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſs for an Explanation of his meaning, but if
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:33608:20"/>
not with him, it may with others leſs preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diced, and manifeſt my Father not to be guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <q>of Errors and Contempt of our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, as he is charged to be, <hi>Animadverſions,</hi> p. 26.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond paſſage is quoted by T. C. <hi>Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mad.</hi> p. 27. His quarrel is with an Expreſſion in the ſaid Book of my Fathers, which runs thus, p. 13. <q>For that which he took upon him was our Garment, even the Fleſh and Blood of our Nature, which is of an earthly periſhing Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</q> Now mark, he ſpeaks in the preſent Tenſe, Our Fleſh and Blood is, and not in the time paſt, his Fleſh and Blood was of an earthly periſhing Nature; 'tis true, 'twas our Garment, Fleſh and Blood like ours; or elſe how could he be perfect Man? But the Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of his Body, was ſo ſeaſoned with the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Salt of the Covenant, (that though in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Fleſh and Blood like ours, yet being without Sin) it could not like ours, (the beſt of whom have at ſome time or other committed Sin) periſh, nor ſee corruption. My Father ſaith, p. 18. <hi>For the Fleſh and Blood of our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, was not his own naturally, but only as he pleaſed to take it upon him, and make it his.</hi> Now if our Fleſh and Blood be of an earthly periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Nature, and Chriſt was a <hi>Man made like unto us in all things, ſin only excepted,</hi> What was it which preſerved his Body from periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but the ſame Almighty Power which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat it, raiſed it from the Dead, and preſerved
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:33608:21"/>
it ſpotleſs, ſo that guile was not found in his Mouth.</p>
            <p>But to ſatisfie all that are Impartial, that my Father was <q>no Contemner nor Undervaluer of the Perſon or Body of Chriſt, nor guilty of making or raiſing an Imaginary <hi>Maulkin</hi> out of his own Brain, as T. C. unſavourly phraſes it, <hi>Animad.</hi> p. 28.</q> I ſhall add two or three Quotations out of the ſame Book, for a Concluſion of the whole Matter.</p>
            <p>Page 7. My Father affirms, <hi>That it is upon Conſideration (and through God's acceptance of this <hi>Sacrifice for Sin</hi>) that the Sins of Believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers are pardoned, that God might be juſt, and the juſtifier of him which believeth in Jeſus, or who is of the Faith of Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Page 14. Speaking concerning the Seed, he Queries, <hi>And is not this the ſame Chriſt that took upon him the Body of Fleſh, and offered it without the Gates of</hi> Jeruſalem? <hi>Is there any more than one? Or is there any other than he? Is Chriſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided? <hi>Is there one Chriſt within, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother without,</hi>
               </hi> &amp;c?</p>
            <p>Page 20. He aſſerts, <hi>That nothing can ſave, but the Knowledge of Chriſt, even of <hi>that very Chriſt, and no other,</hi> who look upon him the prepared Body, and offered it up at</hi> Jeruſalem.</p>
            <p>Now if this be falſe Doctrine, I muſt needs confeſs I know not what is true, neither (I believe) can T. C. inform me, If this be a contemning or undervaluing Chriſt, I know not who honours or exalts him. Let T. C. but pull off thoſe Magnifying and Multiplying
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:33608:21"/>
Spectacles which <hi>G. K.</hi> and <hi>F. B.</hi> have put upon his Noſe, and I queſtion not but the Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors which he thinks he ſees in the Quakers to be ſo numerous, groſs and vile will ſoon va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh. And let him lay aſide all Malice and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice, which appears ſo much in his Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, and then he'll ſee plainly, that the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers are not ſuch Beaſts of Prey, as the Wolve-skins and Bear-skins, which he hath put upon them, repreſents them to be. But if he will wilfully ſhut his Eyes, and inſtead of beholding them as they really are, put frightful Diſguiſes on them, that if poſſible, he might expoſe them to be worried by the Dogs (<hi>viz.</hi> ſuch Men as are for ſnarling at, biting and devouring ſo far as their Power reaches) I queſtion not, but ſome or other will ſtill be ſtirred up to pull them off, as faſt as he puts them on, and likewiſe to ſet forth both him and his Abettors in their proper Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, whereby they may appear really what they are, and ſo may be prevented from de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving Innocent, Well-meaning People with their Slanders and Falſhoods.</p>
            <p>Reader, I beſeech thee bear with me a little, if in making a remarke or two upon a friend of T. C's, and a companion of his, in promoting the work of oppoſition againſt us, I ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain thee a little longer then I intended; for truly I would not concern my ſelf with him, if I thought it worth any body's while that is of more Service; and think me not altogether beſides my ſelf, for medling with ſuch a kind
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:33608:22"/>
of a Man. I confeſs he exceeds mevery eminently in 3 reſpects, <hi>viz.</hi> Age, Whimſies and Malice, &amp; therefore thou muſt needs grant he hath me upon a diſadvantage. Yet though I would reſpect his Age, I cannot but pity his Whim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, and ſlight his Malice; 'tis <hi>John Pennyman</hi> I mean, a Man famous for three things, (the two firſt of which, though I cannot affirm up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my own perſonal knowledge, they being done before my time, yet have them from cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible information; and my ſelf have heard them objected againſt him in publick Meetings, and not by him denyed) <hi>viz.</hi> Firſt, His em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploying a Porter to carry a parcel of Religious Books, amongſt which the Bible is ſaid to be one, to the <hi>Exchange,</hi> with a deſign to burn them openly there: Which what noiſe it made about Town, and what reflections the Quakers met with upon that account, he being eſteemed one of them, I doubt not but divers now living, who are no Quakers, may remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. Secondly, His providing a great number of Veniſon-Paſties (the exact number where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I will not certainly fix, though I was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed it was Twenty ſeven) and a conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel quantity of Wine, and ſending them to <hi>Merchant-Taylors-Hall,</hi> at the publication of his Marriage, (and by the way I would Query, whether J. P. did not uſe the expreſſion of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viting <hi>Jew and Gentile, Barbarian, Scythian, Bond and Free?</hi> And when a great company of all ſorts were met there, whether he did not tell them, <hi>That the Wine was all of a ſort, and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:33608:22"/>
the Meat was all of a ſort, and he that could receive it, let him?</hi>) Where the great waſte that was made, and the rude behaviour of his mixt multitude of gueſts, was ſcandalous to ſober People, I believe not forgotten by divers to this very day. And Thirdly, his inſipid writings, ſtufft with a great deal of envy, little ſenſe, and leſs proof of his Aſſertions; as wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs his two late bits of Paper, given away by him at our Meeting-houſes doors, one publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in 1694. Entituled, <hi>A few words of great Concernment,</hi> and directed to fourteen by name; and in general, to <hi>all the reſt of our Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters.</hi> The other this preſent Year 1695. Entituled, <hi>A Few words of Moment, to be imparted to this Yearly Meeting of the People called Quakers in</hi> London, &amp;c. Yet delivered by him to any that would take them, let them be Quakers or no. Which how <hi>certain and true Teſtimonies they are,</hi> I am now enquiring into, and when I have ſaid what I have to ſay concerning them at preſent, <hi>He that can receive them let him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His firſt Paper ſaith, <hi>Your Miniſtry or Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration is at an end, and muſt more and more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe and dwindle, and for ever be extinct:</hi> From whence I obſerve, he knows not which of them it is that is at an end, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> whether <hi>Miniſtry or Miniſtration;</hi> for it ſeems both are not, or elſe he might have uſed the word <hi>and</hi> inſtead of the word <hi>or.</hi> Secondly, Which ſoever of the two it be that <hi>is at an end,</hi> it muſt ſtill <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe and dwindle,</hi> which ſhews he is got to
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:33608:23"/>
the end of ſenſe, and perfectly nonſenſical; for I think, according to my poor capacity of underſtanding, that what is at an end, is paſt decreaſing or dwindling either. Thirdly, He lumps all our Miniſters by Wholeſale; for 'tis not only the Fourteen, but <hi>all the reſt of our Miniſters</hi> alſo, whom this word of untruth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes; and that, as it is more than he knows or can prove by the Fourteen named, ſo is more than is poſſible for him to know by all the reſt, many of whom he cannot pretend to any knowledge of at all, much leſs can have any thing to object againſt them, either as to Converſation or Doctrine. <hi>But Chriſt's Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> (he tells us) <hi>and his Miniſtration are to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe and flouriſh;</hi> but in Crotchets ſays <hi>[in the appointed ſeaſon]</hi> wherefore upon the whole it appears to me, that theſe <hi>Words of great Concernment,</hi> proceeds not from <hi>The word of Truth,</hi> but from the Crotchets of a Whimſical imagination, whoſe Life lies in quarreling, though he knows not why, nor can give any ſenſible account wherefore. But it muſt be <hi>to the gladding, refreſhing and comforting the Hearts of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pright, Sincere and Single-hearted:</hi> Now if he be one of them, it ſeems ſtrange that <hi>The Word of Truth</hi> he ſpeaks of, if it ever ſpake by him, ſhould never ſend him in time of Perſecution, to the ſaving of him now and then 20 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> which he might have been in proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of loſing, for his Poor Inſignificant ſays. But perhaps the Conſtables and Informers had not <hi>an Ear to hear,</hi> and ſo he would not <hi>let them
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:33608:23"/>
hear</hi> him: Neither might they have received his (ſo called) <hi>certain and true Teſtimony,</hi> and ſo he would not <hi>let them receive it.</hi> However it was, it hap'ned very well for him, for by that means he ſaved his Pocket.</p>
            <p>Well, ſince that Paper in 1694. did not quite blow up the Quakers Miniſtry or Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, out comes another in 1695. of as <hi>Great Moment</hi> perhaps as an Oracle from <hi>Del<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phos,</hi> delivered from the Infallible <hi>Tripus,</hi> and uttered with ſuch Zeal, that if this do not ſtop their Mouths, he may e'ne conclude, that they are paſt his mending; for if this will not do it, I dare engage nothing that <hi>J. P.</hi> can write ever will. He begins with two Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of <hi>Their great Apoſtle and Prophet</hi> (as he calls him) <hi>George Fox,</hi> to manifeſt to them that they ought to be ſilent, <hi>viz. All you that ſpeak, and not from the Mouth of the Lord, are Falſe Prophets;</hi> Weſtmorland <hi>Petit.</hi> p. 5. 1653. <hi>They are Conjurers and Diviners; and their preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is from Conjuration, that is not ſpoken from the Mouth of the Lord;</hi> G. F<hi>'s</hi> Saul<hi>'s Errand,</hi> &amp;c. p. 7. 1654. Now to ſhew he is a Man of uſe and application, he drives the Nail home, and ſays, <hi>If this be true, then are you (who are of his Party, and Preachers among the Quakers) guilty both before God and Men, of being Falſe Prophets, Conjurers, Diviners; and your preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from Conjuration, whereby you deceive and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witch the People.</hi> A high Charge I will aſſure you; but if any ſhould Query, how he clinches this Nail, and what proof he brings to make
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:33608:24"/>
good this Indictment? I anſwer, <hi>John Penny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> hath ſaid it; he from his <hi>vain boaſting and ſelf-exalted Spirit, is to teſtifie to them,</hi> viz. <hi>That they do not preach from the Mouth of the Lord, as they pretend.</hi> And he, from the <hi>vain Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of</hi> his own <hi>proud, deceived and deceitful Heart, is to warn them, That they preſume not to Preach any more in the Name of the Lord, till they come into deep Humility,</hi> &amp;c. Therefore to ſilence them, <hi>J. P.</hi> hath ſent forth his Bull, and forbids them; (but be he never ſo curſt, one good turn is, he hath but ſhort Horns). And if this be not <hi>a certain and true Teſtimony,</hi> and proof enough too to ſatisfie the Reader, that they <hi>are guilty</hi> of this Charge, <hi>both before God and Men,</hi> he may e'ne go ſeek for proof elſewhere, though <hi>J. P.</hi> (no doubt) would have him think it enough: But if he ſhould chance to inſiſt upon more, he may look it where he can find it, for <hi>J. P.</hi> will afford him no more: Nor indeed is it reaſonable to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect any more in ſuch a ſcrap of Paper; and ſince <hi>J. P.</hi> is at ſo much Charge and Pains as to Print them, and come to our Meeting-houſe Doors to give them away, han't he done e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough? Ay, and too much too, (I think) and therefore for this time pray put it up, and be thankful. But wherefore his Confederate <hi>F. B.</hi> ſhould Print this Paſſage of <hi>G. F</hi>'s I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not conceive; for if it be true, as <hi>J. P.</hi> ſeems to grant, what will become of <hi>F. B</hi>'s Paſtor, and his Brethren of the Clergy, who do not ſo much as pretend to <hi>ſpeak from the Mouth of
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:33608:24"/>
the Lord</hi> by immediate Inſpiration? And if <hi>F.B.</hi> do not grant it, they may chance to weaken their Cauſe by differing among themſelves. Moreover, if that Man may be ſaid to be of a <hi>Party</hi> with another, who agrees with him in his Sentiments, then thus far is J. P. <hi>of Party</hi> with <hi>G. F.</hi> by granting theſe Quotations, and not only he, but all Speakers or Preachers that are of Party with him therein, or in the Work he thereby promotes; and ſo let them take thoſe Quotations, and J. P's Concluſions, and make the Application themſelves, and the uſe he makes of it too, <hi>viz. Not to preſume to Preach,</hi> (and I may add, or write either) till the Work he mentions is wrought in them, viz. <hi>They be come into deep Humility, and out of their Vain-boaſting, and Self-exalted Spirit they are at preſent found in.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now after all the preceding Objections a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>J. P.</hi> I ſincerely declare, that the good Character I have heard concerning him as to his upright Dealing between Man and Man in Way of Commerce, and ſome other Points of Morality, for which I have heard him Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended, hath often raiſed a Pity in me to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him, and a deſire he might not loſe the Reward of them, by his defect in reſpect to Chriſtianity, the Chiefeſt Point whereof is Charity, and the want of which ſpoils all the other Parts of a Man's Religion, and without which a Man cannot indeed be truly Religious, according to the right definition of Religion. And I do at this time heartily deſire on his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:33608:25"/>
that he may meet with true Repentance, for all that through Malice he hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>acted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us; (which truly I do in great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſure attribute to the weakneſs of his Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and the Whimſies of his Brain, which he hath ſo evidently and frequently manifeſted in divers of his Actions) leſt the Judgment which came upon his Brother <hi>Jeffery Bullock, viz.</hi> a Deſpairing Death-bed overtake him.</p>
            <p>And Reader, if thy Inclination farther leads thee to be informed of our Holy Religion, and the unholy Treatment it and we have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived at the Hands of our Adverſaries, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially Apoſtates, ſuch as T. C. F. B. G. K. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the many Tracts that have been written in defence thereof, againſt the Miſrepreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Perverſions of our Enemies, which for theſe Twenty Years and upwards, have from time to time been publiſhed, to nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous here to nominate, will more at large in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form thee: And are ſold by <hi>Tace Sowle,</hi> next Door to our Meeting-Houſe in <hi>White-hart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>court</hi> in <hi>Gracious-ſtreet;</hi> and by <hi>Thomas Northcot,</hi> in <hi>George-yard</hi> in <hi>Lumbard-ſtreet,</hi> Bookſellers.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:33608:25"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
